Mrs. Ritu Seth
Contact No. - 8130549201
Email - sethritu3@gmail.com

Career Summary:

Accomplished educator with demonstrated ability to teach, motivate and direct students while maintaining high interest and achievements. An articulate communicator able to effectively interact with diverse population of students at a variety of academic levels. Constantly maintained excellent relations with students, parents, faculty and administrators. Self motivated with strong planning, organizational and leadership skills. Worked as T.G.T(Science), Academic Coordinator in reputed schools of Delhi and Gurgram. Also, worked as a Headmistress in the 'Paras World School' and the 'Summer Fields School', Gurugram.

Special Achievements:

- Certified Microsoft Innovative Educator Expert (MIEE) for the past 4 years.
- Completed a 15 day workshop on KED Philosophy organized at Kunskappskolan, Gurgaon.
- Conducted workshop for parents on the teaching of Mathematics to class
 3- 5 through the "JodoGyan" methodology.
- Attended and conducted workshop for teachers on "Using Group Discussion in class" organized by Learn Today
- Completed a six day workshop on "Multiple Intelligence" organized by Learn Today at Vasant Valley School.
- Attended a workshop on "Leadership Skills" by Mr. Arun Kapoor and Ms.
 Nitya of Learn Today at Vasant Valley School.
- Attended a workshop on "Teachers as Mentors" by Mr. Gulraj Shahpuri.
- Attended a workshop on "Innovative Science" by Mr. Pierce Fontes at Vasant Valley School.
- Attended a workshop on "Setting up a Science Activity Centre" by Mr. Arvind Gupta at Shriram School, Vasant Vihar.

- Attended a workshop on "Integrated Projects with the Teaching Learning Process" by Ms. Moloyashree Hashmi at Shriram School, Vasant Vihar
- Completed the beginner's course of the INTEL Teach to The Future Program.

Work Experience

- 1. Summer Field School, Gurugram
 - Headmistress (March 2019 May,2020)
 - Handled the entire Junior wing of the school, comprising of 610 students and 52 mentors. Sharing the glimpse of the accomplished duties.
 - Planned curriculum and effective implementation
 - Trained mentors for 21st century skills, life skills, progressive pedagogies, inclusive education and team building.
 - Redesigned assessment policy abreast with progressive methodologies.
 - Teacher's observations, feedback and the way forward.
 - Budget for junior block.
 - Superintended safety and security of students and staff.
 - Supervised bus routes and resolved issues if any.
 - Directed special days, assemblies, activities (Interschool and Intraschool) and junior school events.
 - Resolved all the parents' issues related to academic and admin of junior block.
 - Shared daily report of junior block to the principal.
 - Fostered the school philosophy and ethos to the community.
 - Instilled life skills to grade V.

2. The Paras World School, Gurugram

- Academic Head (July,2015 till February 2018)
- Headmistress (March 2018 March 2019)
 - Coordinated all the academic and co curricular work
 - Unit plans (Theme Plans) and weekly lesson plans
 - Planning and overseeing worksheets
 - M.L.V's Making learning visible.
 - Integrated projects and holiday H.W
 - Weekly Newsletters
 - Organized Field trips and Excursions Theme related
 - Time table and substitutions on daily basis and taught Science.
 - Organized special days and special subject weeks.
 - Organized special assemblies.
 - Coordinated for workshops and in house trainings for teachers.
 - Coordinated with teachers and overlooking of smooth functioning of the school in absence of Principal.
 - Coordinated various events like Annual Day, Sports Day and various inter-school and intra school events.

3. Suncity School, Gurgaon- (March 2014 - May 2015)

Taught as M.Y.P – Biology of grades VI – VIII.

4. The Ridge Valley School, Gurgaon - (2010 to 2014)

- Academic Coordinator- Responsibilities included-
- Planning the integrated webs of the academic and curriculum activities, overseeing worksheets and lesson planning for all subjects, designing class specific projects and relevant visits for enhancing and engaging student activities.

- Time Table Incharge Responsibilities included, preparing Time Table for Nursery to grade VII and put substitutions for teachers on daily basis.
- Olympiad Incharge- Successfully conducted Olympiads (Science, Maths, English and Cyber) of grades I - VII.
- Overlooked smooth functioning of the school in the absence of H.O.P.S.
- Coordinated various Inter and Intra school activities and visits.
- Taught Science to grades IV VII and established Science Lab for the school
- Coordinated various events like Annual Day, Environment week, Earth Day, Adventure camp and Sports Day each year.
- Established Science Lab for the school and conducted Science experiments and related activities.

5. Delhi Public School, Sector 45, Gurgaon (2002-2010)

Joined the school on 23.4.2002 and taught General Science to grades III- V.

- (a) Representated as a class representative of grade IV and V.
- (b) Detailed responsibilities included:
 - Coordination of all the sections of grades IV and V(Admn)
 - Handling of new admissions
 - Handling of parent's complaints
 - Event coordination- Events (100% participation), Special Assemblies (Theme Related)
- (c) Worked as a Science coordinator of grades III- V. Responsibilities included:
 - Coordination for initializing General Science curriculum Lesson Planning, concept sheets, syllabus, assignments and assessment papers.
 - Established Science Lab for the school and conducted Science experiments and related activities.
 - Coordinated and planned environmental related events like Earth Day, Water Day, Environment Day and took active part in

Founder's day, Annual Day, Sports Day and various intra and inter school activities.

6. American Montessori Public School, Gurgaon (2000-2002)

Taught Science to grades V- VIII. Took up the challenge to plan and establish the Science lab of the school.

7. Lancers Convent School, Rohini – (1993-1994)

Worked as a Science teacher of grades III- V.

8. Delhi Public School, Mathura Road, Delhi (1990-1991 end)

Worked as T.G.T(Science) of grades VI - VIII.

Education:

- B. Sc. (General) from Ajmer University, Rajasthan in 1988 Chemistry,
 Zoology and Botany
- ➤ B. Ed. From M D University, Rohtak, 1989
- M.A (English) from Swami Vivekanand Subharti University, Meerut.

Personal:

In a career spanning over 26 years, I have had the experience of working in schools run by diverse institutions ranging from D.P.S Matura Road to the Summer Field School, Gurugram. The parents and children in each of these schools were from diverse backgrounds and that has been an added advantage for me to grow as I have learnt to adapt to different kind of environment and philosophies.

My husband has a distinguished a career as Chartered Accountant in Multinational companies and have two children studying in collages.